Hello and welcome to our lecture on computer
architecture. Now to some degree that might seem
like a contradiction in terms because the whole
name of the course is computer architecture. But
we're kind of at the point where we have gotten
to the level where we've built up enough basic
stuff to really start talking about computer
architecture. Like what's a central processing
unit? We know what gates are. We're going to start
with the gates. We're not going to worry about
transistors. We're not going to worry about tubes.
We're not going to worry about slide rules. And
then we're going to just go from there. Actually,
for me, this phase is a little more comfortable.
I was never a computer engineer or electrical
engineer and I kind of understand transistors.
And so that first half was kind of fun for me to
do a bunch of research for you and share with you
what I thought was important about transistors
and tubes, etc. But now we're going to start
with gates. What can we do with an ANDgate,
an ORgate, notgate, exclusive or etc. First,
we're going to learn how to start adding numbers
because calculation and multiplication and
addition are important. Learn about full adders
and half adders. We have to learn about number
representation. How do computers represent
numbers? Base 2, base 10, and hexadesimal.
Then we're going to figure out how we actually
store data using gates to store data. We'll learn
about latches and flip-flops. And once we start
getting larger and more complicated circuits,
we're starting to talk about delay and speed and
clock rate and all those kinds of things. And
then we'll start thinking about how you build a
computer that can execute programs, machine code,
where you write software in zeros and ones. And
then ultimately we'll take a look at how CPUs are
put together, the architecture of CPUs. So, we
often start with computer architecture to talk
about the whole computer. Like there's there's
things like motherboards. Let me let me give you
a close-up view of a motherboard, but actually
this really isn't just any old motherboard. When
I started teaching programming back in 2008, this
was the motherboard that I would pass around the
class. This is from a desktop computer. It's a I
think it's probably like a 300 megahertz computer,
which is really slow. Um, I also passed around
the CPU that went to this. So, there's the CPU
that went to this particular computer. And, and I
passed it around the class because I wanted people
to feel I wanted them to feel the the wires that
come out of these things to get a sense of this
is all very electrical. And I've been talking
from the beginning of the course to the level
of this is all very electrical. So, if you look
at the back of this, there are little tiny wires,
many of them going on like little streets
and chips are like buildings that are in
in a neighborhood and the wires go between them.
And the other thing I wanted people to do is like
pass this around cuz you can't feel it here, but
these are kind of pointy little things where the
chips and connectors come through the board and
they're soldered together and that's where these
connectors are connecting to these wires. And so
I just wanted people to get a sense that inside of
a computer there was something and it was physical
and it was a thing and like a CPU. The CPU has has
little pins on it and I wanted people to touch the
pins. You can see many people over the years have
touched these pins and they're they're all bent
up. And so here I have I used to pass around this
memory chip. And again, this is all from 2008 so
that people could get a physical feeling of what
was inside of computers doing all of this work.
So generally if you think about all those wires,
they generally are taking a zero or a one back
and forth. And that's the what we like about
gates. And gates simplify the analogeness of all
circuits and make it so that we can think of them
digitally. And so this is a slide from a lecture
that I created in 2008 where I basically said
this is what a computer does. It has a central
processing unit which processes instructions.
It has main memory which is where the instructions
and data are stored. It has secondary memory which
is like disk drives where you save files and load
data etc. And databases live on disk drives and
then put output devices like keyboards and mice
and things like that. And so the definitions that
I used back then were a central processing unit
runs the program. The CPU's programmed physically
to wonder what to do next. It's not really smart,
but it is very very fast and we program it to be
smart. Right. Um, input devices like keyboard,
mouse and touchcreen. Output devices like the
screen, speakers, printer, DVD burner or whatever.
Main memory is small, fast, temporary storage.
And secondary memory is the larger, more permanent
storage that you can power cycle and not come off.
And so this notion that central processing units
are built to think about what next means that we
are inside the computer. When we write software,
we live in the main memory of the computer and
our instructions feed the what next that the CPU
and we'll see toward the end we'll understand with
the fetch execute cycle which is fetch. What is
it I'm supposed to do next? I did that. Now grab
the next one. That's the fetch execute cycle. Now
we can program this in something like say Python.
But really it's not. It's really programmed in
machine language which is zeros and ones. And by
the end of this lecture and the beginning of
the next lecture, you will be programming in
zeros and ones. Believe me, this this one's
a little this one is a little difficult. So
you just take your time and follow along with
how this goes. And so from the last lecture,
we really saw the growth of transistors where we
had 16 transistors on a little tiny circuit to
laying out hundreds and millions and billions of
transistors on little tiny chips. And so with that
we can create increasingly complicated processes.
Now the way this design process usually works and
we did VSSI layout in the previous lectures. We
tend not to do VSSI layout for modern computers.
We tend to build reusable components like an adder
or a latch or something like that and then we wire
those all together and then software takes our
abstract design of gates and latches that that
think in terms of zeros and ones and components
like adders and multipliers and ripal carry adders
etc. and then turn that into a transistor layout.
And some of the things that computer CPUs do are
so important like adding and multiplying and like
little caches and registers that we might tune the
the hardware layout in the transistors a little
bit. But in general software does all of the work
and takes our abstract design and turns it into an
optimal layout for our chip. And then of course we
use photo lithography. So up next we're going to
talk about how we use gates to add numbers. Again,
going to the point where we have gates.
Now, how can we construct multiple gate
circuits that accomplish the kinds of
things that microprocessors want to do?